<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Chrome extension | Undefined NULL]]></title>
  <link href="https://www.undefinednull.com/blog/categories/chrome-extension/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://www.undefinednull.com/"/>
  <updated>2017-07-06T20:33:49+05:30</updated>
  <id>https://www.undefinednull.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Shidhin]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Whatsapp web client: Hide/blur thumbnail images preview]]></title>
    <link href="https://www.undefinednull.com/2015/02/04/whatsapp-web-client-hide-slash-blur-thumbnail-images-preview/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-04T15:37:17+05:30</updated>
    <id>https://www.undefinednull.com/2015/02/04/whatsapp-web-client-hide-slash-blur-thumbnail-images-preview</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The most anticipated Whatsapp web is here finally. If you haven&rsquo;t seen it go check it out: <a href="http://web.whatsapp.com">http://web.whatsapp.com</a>. I really like it because of these reasons:</p>

<ol>
<li>Desktop notifications in chrome</li>
<li>I don&rsquo;t need to check my phone whenever any message is arrived. The chat window is in the right corner of my screen.</li>
<li><strong>The main one:</strong> I can type as fast as writing an email or using a chat application.</li>
</ol>


<!-- more -->


<h2>But is it a complete Whatsapp client ?</h2>

<p>Not yet. Basically the web client mirror the Whatsapp application from the phone. That&rsquo;s why they say that Whatsapp application in your phone should be connected to internet when you use the web client.</p>

<p>Besides, the whatsapp web client lacks many functions provided by the mobile app. For example: You cannot forward message/media from one window to another. You cannot stop the media ( Images ) autodownload .. etc</p>

<h2>Is media autodownload required for a web client ?</h2>

<p>I know that Whatsapp has an option to stop media auto-download mainly for reducing network data consumption. That&rsquo;s said, it should not be a problemfor the web client.</p>

<p>But what about user&rsquo;s privacy ? When you receive any images/videos in your mobile phone, there are less chances that others going to see it ( as the mobile screen is small ). But you&rsquo;re going to use the web client from your laptop/desktop, may be from a public cafe or even from your office. Chances are more for others to see your chats. And whatsapp web doesn&rsquo;t have any option to stop the auto-download images.</p>

<h2>Solution</h2>

<p>I use whatsapp web and I had the same problem. That&rsquo;s when I decided to make a Chrome extension to solve this issue. I did publish it in the Chrome webstore, and you can install it from here:</p>

<p><strong><a href="https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/whatsapp-web-hide-media-i/elioehejcldpnphaohhkcdjhjojjbkim">WhatsApp web Hide Images Chrome Extension</a></strong></p>

<p>Preview:</p>

<p><img src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/u8Y1oIPCC_ejXU5OlpQJIxZCHEJr5Fx-HsV9UzG6KnR0gk6VmrkcHnN-QjRCQRqbMTy5xnTM=s640-h400-e365" alt="screenshot" /></p>

<p>The extension will not stop the media auto-download. But it will hide all the thumbnail images by default. On mouseover, a transparent image will be shown, and onclick it will show the full image. I hope this will be useful to some of you guys.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
