<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[S H I D H I N . C . R]]></title>
  <link href="http://shidhincr.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://shidhincr.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-10-03T18:34:59+05:30</updated>
  <id>http://shidhincr.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Shidhin C R]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[ Some Gotchas In Arithmetic Expression Evaluation : JavaScript]]></title>
    <link href="http://shidhincr.com/2013/09/26/some-gotchas-in-arithmetic-expression-evaluation-javascript/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-26T16:15:00+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://shidhincr.com/2013/09/26/some-gotchas-in-arithmetic-expression-evaluation-javascript</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Solve a small problem in JavaScript</h2>

<p>This post is just for recollecting some of the basics of JavaScript. Let&rsquo;s start with a small JavaScript code. Here is the code –– Solve it with out using the console.</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='javascript'><span class='line'><span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">a</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mi">5</span><span class="p">;</span> <span class="nx">b</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mi">3</span><span class="p">;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nx">a</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="p">(</span> <span class="nx">a</span> <span class="o">-</span> <span class="p">(</span> <span class="nx">b</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="p">(</span> <span class="nx">a</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nx">a</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="nx">b</span> <span class="p">)</span> <span class="o">-</span> <span class="nx">b</span> <span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">);</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Take your own time to come up with an answer before moving to the next section.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Analysing the problem</h2>

<p>If your answer is <code>a = 3 and b = 5</code>, this post is written for you. Open your favourite browser and fire up the console. Put the above code in the console and see the values of <code>a</code> and <code>b</code> now.</p>

<p>Stunned ?  Yeah, The values of <code>a</code> and <code>b</code> are <code>a = 0  and b = 5</code> now. Honestly I also got it wrong initially. I did ask this question to some of my friends ( who are in JavaScript circle ),  and all of them gave me wrong answer.</p>

<h2>Some flashback</h2>

<p>So, here is how I arrived this to particular question. Last week I was trying to write the code for an interview problem in JavaScript  and it&rsquo;s a very common interview question –– How to swap values of 2 variables with out using a 3rd variable.</p>

<p>Let the variables be <code>a = 5</code> and <code>b = 3</code>. Swap the values of <code>a</code> and <code>b</code> with out using any 3rd variable .</p>

<p>Solution is simple . Just do the following arithmetic operations</p>

<pre><code>a = a + b
b = a - b
a = a - b
</code></pre>

<p>This will do the job.</p>

<p>What I was trying is to write the entire expression in one single line. I wrote it like below.</p>

<p><strong>Code 1 :</strong></p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='javascript'><span class='line'><span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">a</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mi">5</span><span class="p">;</span> <span class="nx">b</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mi">3</span><span class="p">;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nx">a</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="p">(</span> <span class="nx">a</span> <span class="o">-</span> <span class="p">(</span> <span class="nx">b</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="p">(</span> <span class="nx">a</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nx">a</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="nx">b</span> <span class="p">)</span> <span class="o">-</span> <span class="nx">b</span> <span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">);</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Cool .. I thought it&rsquo;s done.</p>

<p>But I got surpriced when I tried it in the console. I was expecting final values should be <code>a = 3 and b = 5</code> but the output was different. I got <code>a = 0 and b =5</code>.</p>

<p>WTF ? Let me change the code a bit. I modifed the code like this</p>

<p><strong>Code 2 :</strong></p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='javascript'><span class='line'><span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">a</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mi">5</span><span class="p">;</span> <span class="nx">b</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mi">3</span><span class="p">;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nx">a</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="p">(</span> <span class="p">(</span> <span class="nx">b</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="p">(</span> <span class="nx">a</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nx">a</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="nx">b</span> <span class="p">)</span> <span class="o">-</span> <span class="nx">b</span> <span class="p">)</span> <span class="o">-</span> <span class="nx">a</span> <span class="p">);</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>
This time I got the correct results <code>a = -3 and b = 5</code>. So why the hell it didnt work for the first expression ?</p>

<h2>The answer is :</h2>

<p>We&rsquo;re evaluating it wrongly. I mean we are not doing the way JavaScript engine does. I went to the EcmaScript specification and read the section for &ldquo;Arithmetic Expression&rdquo;.</p>

<blockquote><p>Expressions : Any valid unit code that resolves to some value.</p></blockquote>

<p><strong>Two things to note :</strong></p>

<ul>
<li>Assignment operators are right to left associative. That means for the expression <code>a = b = 5</code>, the value <code>5</code> will be assigned to variable <code>b</code> and then assigned to variable <code>b</code>.</li>
<li>Arithmetic and multiplicative operators are left to right associative. For the expression <code>c = a + b</code>, the value of <code>a</code> will be computed first, then goes to <code>b</code> and computes it&rsquo;s value.</li>
</ul>


<p>For our problem, if I draw the parse tree roughly, it will be like below.</p>

<pre><code>   =
 /   \
a     -
    /   \
   a     =
       /   \
      b     -
          /   \
         =      b
       /   \
      a     +
          /   \
         a     b
</code></pre>

<p>Ideally parse tree doesn&rsquo;t contain the <code>=</code> operator. I made it like this to understand how the parser start evaluating the expression.</p>

<p>In the above parse tree, all the <code>=</code> operators are evaluated from right-to left ( that means the right node will be evaluated first and the value will be assigned to the left node ). On the other hand, arithmetic/multiplicative expressions are evaluated from left to right ( that means the values will be assigned from left and the arithmetic/multiplicative operation will be carried out ).</p>

<p>We can identify sub-expressions in our code. Basically, we can extract the expressions containing <code>=</code> to sub-expressions. Hence the above parse tree can be re-drawn like below.</p>

<pre><code>   =
 /   \
a     -
    /   \
   a     X
</code></pre>

<p>Where <code>X</code> is the <strong>Sub-Expression 1</strong> given below :</p>

<pre><code>         =
       /   \
      b     -
          /   \
         Y     b
</code></pre>

<p>Where <code>Y</code> is the <strong>Sub-Expression 2</strong> given below :</p>

<pre><code>         =
       /   \
      a     +
          /   \
         a     b
</code></pre>

<p>Let&rsquo;s see how JavaScript parser evaluate the value of <code>a</code> finally.</p>

<h3>Steps :</h3>

<ol>
<li><p>Parser takes the main expression <code>a = a - X</code> and evaluated from left to right. At first, parser finds the variable<code>a</code> and finds it&rsquo;s value. Now the parser moves to the next variable <code>X</code> and try to calculate it&rsquo;s value. Since <code>X</code> is an expression, it need to be evaluated to form a premitive value.</p>

<p> <em>Note: To get the value, parser internally calls the <a href="http://es5.github.io/#x8.7.1">GetValue</a> of each operands</em></p>

<p> So, for the parser, the expression becomes  like this :</p>

<p> <code>a = GetValue( a ) - GetValue( Evaluate( X ) )</code></p>

<p> Which is :</p>

<p> <code>a = 5 - GetValue( Evaluate( X )</code></p></li>
<li><p>Now it need to evaluate the expression <code>X</code> where <code>b = Y - b</code>. Here the first operand <code>Y</code> itself a sub-expression, so parser has to evaluate it first before calcualting the value of the second operand <code>b</code>.</p></li>
<li><p>Let&rsquo;s evaluate the expression <code>Y</code> which is <code>a = a + b</code>. This is straightforward and contains no sub expression , hence evaluated like this.</p>

<p> <code>a = GetValue( a ) + GetValue( b )</code>
 This equals to :</p>

<p> <code>a = 5 + 3</code></p>

<p> Finally the value of expression <code>Y</code> becomes <code>8</code>.</p></li>
<li><p>Coming back to step 2 where expression <code>X</code> needs to be completed. expression <code>X</code> is</p>

<p> <code>b = GetValue( Y ) - GetValue( b )</code></p>

<p> Becomes like this :</p>

<p> <code>b = 8 - GetValue( b )</code></p>

<p> Which is :</p>

<p> <code>b = 8 - 3</code></p>

<p> Finally the value of <code>b</code> and expression <code>X</code> becomes <code>5</code>.</p></li>
<li><p>So now all the sub expressions are evaluated , the main expression can be completed now.</p>

<p> The main expression was :</p>

<p> <code>a = 5 - GetValue( X ) and value of X = 5</code></p>

<p>That means final value of <code>a = 5 - 5</code>  which is <code>0</code>.</p></li>
<li><p>Finally the values of <code>a</code> and <code>b</code> will become <code>a = 0 and b = 5</code></p></li>
</ol>


<p>Now we&rsquo;re in the same direction with JS engine. We can apply what we learnt for the <strong>Code 2</strong> also.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>I didn&rsquo;t want to write these much long. All I wanted to recollect those basics. Thanks for reading !!</p>

<p> References :</p>

<ol>
<li><a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/JavaScript/Guide/Expressions_and_Operators">https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/JavaScript/Guide/Expressions_and_Operators</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.ecma-international.org/ecma-262/5.1/#sec-8.7">http://www.ecma-international.org/ecma-262/5.1/#sec-8.7</a></li>
<li><a href="http://es5.github.io/#x8.7.1">http://es5.github.io/#x8.7.1</a></li>
<li><a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/19045411/can-somebody-explain-how-javascript-arithmetic-expressions-work">http://stackoverflow.com/questions/19045411/can-somebody-explain-how-javascript-arithmetic-expressions-work</a></li>
</ol>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Starting my new blog: Finally Octopress]]></title>
    <link href="http://shidhincr.com/2013/09/25/starting-my-new-blog-finally-octopress/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-25T07:36:00+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://shidhincr.com/2013/09/25/starting-my-new-blog-finally-octopress</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Finally Octopress !!</h2>

<p>I wanted to start writing blog ever since I started coding. I never had a success setting it up because of time constraints and many other reasons. During this time, I&rsquo;ve evaluated a number of blogging platforms and eventually I thought of using wordpress as my blogging platform when I start my blog.</p>

<p>Now finally I&rsquo;m having some time. I decided to spend some time everyday dedicating to my blog. So first thing I need to do is setting up a wordpress blog with default template.</p>

<p>I started browsing to find a good theme for the wordpress blog before setting up anything. While browsing, I opened <strong><a href="http://www.paulirish.com">paulirish.com</a></strong> and saw that he&rsquo;d recently switched his blog to some new blogging software called Octopress.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>I also read about Octopress from my daily reading list, but didn&rsquo;t give much attention to it. But I found Paul&rsquo;s blog very neat –– The default theme of Octopress is awesome –– and it&rsquo;s responsive too. I started checking out all Octopress blogs, and how to configure it. Finally I decided to use Octopress for my blog.</p>

<h3>Why Octopress and not Wordpress ?</h3>

<p>Octopress is simple and comes up with a neat, elegant ( and responsive ) theme. Obviously Wordpress is really the most powerful and most widely used blogging software, and it has lot of extentions and plugins available. But for me , for writing some tech tips , don&rsquo;t need all those stuff. Using Octopress , I can use familiar git commands , write everything in markdown and finally can deploy to github pages.</p>

<p>Another thing I liked is, all my blog content will be residing in my system itself in the form of markdown files. I can generate my static blog site anytime I need and deploy to number of hosting services. The advantage of a static website over a dynamic platform like Wordpress is : It&rsquo;s loading time will be faster. Because everytime I access a blog post in Wordpress, it need to fetch from the database. But Octopress blog will have only static html pages –– so it will be loaded faster.</p>

<h3>How to set up an Octopress blog ?</h3>

<p>This had been covered in many articles. Just google around , you can find a lot. I followed these simple instructions given in the Octopress website. Link is given below</p>

<p><a href="http://octopress.org/docs/deploying/github/">http://octopress.org/docs/deploying/github/</a></p>

<p>There&rsquo;re couple of good themes built for Octopress ( It&rsquo;s all 3rd party ). Since I like the default Octopress theme, I didn&rsquo;t try any 3rd party themes. But It&rsquo;s worth checking out those.</p>

<p>PS: I&rsquo;ll be writing mainly about Javascript , HTML ,CSS and client side framework and design patterns here. Expect more posts from me soon in this space.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
