<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Regular Expressions | Coding The Web]]></title>
  <link href="http://webcod.in/blog/categories/regular-expressions/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://webcod.in/"/>
  <updated>2014-02-25T18:36:12+05:30</updated>
  <id>http://webcod.in/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Shidhin C R]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Starting VerbalRegex.com open source project]]></title>
    <link href="http://webcod.in/2014/01/29/starting-verbalregex-dot-com-open-source-project/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-29T01:09:00+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://webcod.in/2014/01/29/starting-verbalregex-dot-com-open-source-project</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>On the other day, while exploring the Github repositories, this one grabbed my attention.</p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/VerbalExpressions/JSVerbalExpressions">https://github.com/VerbalExpressions/JSVerbalExpressions</a></p>

<p>I like this idea so much. In fact, I also were trying to build something similar. Writing regular expressions were always a tedious task for me. I&rsquo;ve tried learning it enormous times, but still when I want to construct one, I&rsquo;ve to google around.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>So that&rsquo;s why this project got my interest. The idea is pretty cool; Instead of remembering all those complex patterns of regular expressions, I can just use the simple API provided by the library. That&rsquo;s really cool!</p>

<p>But again, There&rsquo;s a limitation: It&rsquo;s just a JavaScript library that can be used inside the code only. What I really wanted is an user interface where I can use some simple steps –– mostly like the API methods of the above library –– to build my final regular expression.</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s when I started working on a new website called <a href="VerbalRegex.com">http://wwww.verbalregex.com</a>. The website is not live yet. I&rsquo;ve created the repository in Github and started working on the UI of it.</p>

<ul>
<li><p>The tools used so far are:</p>

<pre><code>- Yeo man for scaffolding
- AngularJS 
- Angular UI and Twitter Bootstrap
- Grunt
- Karma ( unit testing )
</code></pre></li>
</ul>


<p>The project is in the very early stage. I&rsquo;ve invited some of my friends for the contribution. Once all the designs and requirements ready, the project will find it&rsquo;s momentum.</p>

<p>Here is a screenshot of what I&rsquo;ve built so far.</p>

<p><img src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-oNcO5nhOIwQ/UugGMrn13mI/AAAAAAAAG_c/DSUWGrNxGAw/w958-h495-no/Screen+Shot+2014-01-29+at+1.03.33+am.png" alt="verbalregex.com" /></p>

<p>I&rsquo;m trying to work more on this project on my spare times. Hope everything will go well !!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
